Matthew Rees

Applied Ecologist

Curriculum Vitae September 2020 **♀** School of Biosciences, University of Melbourne

matthewreesearch.com

+61 412 560 534

matt.wayne.rees@gmail.com

@matt_w_reesmatt-w-reesmatthew-w-rees

Profile

I use quantitative methods to improve conservation monitoring, management and decision-making. I specialise in modelling population dynamics and species interactions, focusing on invasive predators. I'm well-versed in field ecology which motivates me to consider what is feasible on-ground and fits within socio-economic constraints. More broadly, I'm passionate about transparent, collaborative science to address real-world conservation problems. I am currently finishing up my PhD with the *Quantitative and Applied Ecology group* while tackling the occasional, related contracting job.

Skills overview

- Extensive fieldwork experience in rugged and remote environments, leading camera-trapping and small mammal live-trapping surveys. 4WD (manual) and remote first aid qualifications.
- > Supervision and training of large fieldwork teams.
- ➤ Storing and analysing large ecological datasets
- > Spatial analysis in R and QGIS software, integration with Shiny applications.
- Quantitative ecological statistics in R: spatial capture-recapture, multi-species occupancy, generalised additive models and structured decision-making methods.

Education

2017-present	PhD (Conservation Biology)	University of Melbourne	
	Interactions between invasive predators and native prey		
2013-2016	Bachelor of Environmental Science (1st class Honours)	Queensland University of Technology	
	Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin, Australia		

Professional Experience

2019-2020	Ecologist (private contractor)	Winda-mara Aboriginal Corporation, Treetec	
	Training Indigenous rangers in fauna monitoring protocols and grant writing		
2020-2020	Research assistant Designing fox density field surveys	University of Melbourne	
2018-2020	Demonstrator Conservation Biology, Environmental Risk Assessment subjects	University of Melbourne	

Publications

Peer-reviewed

- 1. MW Rees, J Carwardine, A Reeson and J Firn (2020). Rapidly assessing cobenefits to advance threat-management alliances. *Conservation Biology*. https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.13490
- 2. **MW Rees**, JH Pascoe, BA Wintle, M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum and BA Hradsky (2019). Unexpectedly high densities of feral cats in a rugged temperate forest. *Biological Conservation*, 239, 108287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2019. 108287

In peer-review

- 1. H Davies, Tiwi Land Rangers, **MW Rees**, D Stokeld, A Miller, G Gillespie and B Murphy. Variation in feral cat density between two large adjacent islands in Australia's monsoon tropics. *Austral Ecology*.
- 2. M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum, **MW Rees**, BA Hradsky, AR Weeks, A Van Rooyen and JH Pascoe. Genetic sampling and an activity index indicate contrasting lethal control outcomes. *Journal of Wildlife Management*.

Reports

1. MW Rees (2020). Monitoring and managing critical weight range mammals in the indigenous protected areas of the world heritage Budj Bim cultural landscape. A report prepared for the Victorian Government, Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning.

In preparation for peer-review

- 1. **MW Rees**, JH Pascoe, BA Wintle, A Robley, M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum and BA Hradsky. Quantifying the mesopredator release hypothesis: invasive red foxes limit feral cat density in temperate forests.
- 2. **MW Rees**, A Robley, BA Hradsky, BA Wintle, JH Pascoe and N Golding. Modelling spatio-temporal species interactions using generalised additive models.
- 3. **MW Rees**, BA Hradsky, BA Wintle, JH Pascoe & A Robley. Is the patchy site-occupancy of threatened native mammals driven by invasive predators?
- 4. J Bourne, A Basu & **MW Rees**. Automating camera-trap study workflows with performance machine learning models: how does accuracy impact ecological inference?

Grants and awards

2020	University of Melbourne, School of Biosciences, Jasper Loftus-Hills award	\$2.25K
2020	University of Melbourne, School of Biosciences, travel grant	\$2K
2020	Ecological Society of Australia, Hoslworth research endowment	\$7.5K
2019	Ecological Society of Australia, Hoslworth research endowment	\$6.75K
2018	Conservation Ecology Centre student scholarship	\$5K
2017	Victorian Environmental Assesment Council, Bill Borthwick scholarship	\$2K
2017	Victorian Government, Parks Victoria research partners program (co-investigator)	\$20K
2017	Victorian Government, Department of Land, Environment, Land, Water and Planning research grant	\$15K
2017	Victorian Government, Department of Land, Environment, Land, Water and Planning, PhD top-up scholarship	\$15K
2017	Australian federal government, RTP PhD scholarship	\$98K
2016	Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation, honours top-up scholarship	\$10K
2015	University of Wollongong, undergraduate research scholarship	\$7.2K

Presentations

- ➤ International Statistical Ecology Conference (virtual), June 2020. Using spatial mark-resight and GAMs to infer predator interactions.
- ➤ Guest lecture, University of Melbourne, Australian Wildlife Biology, May 2020, Invasive mammals in Australia.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Launceston, November 2019, Does fox control increase feral cat population density?
- ➤ Wimmera Biodiversity Seminar, Rupanyup, September 2019, Monitoring predators and prey in south-west VIC.
- Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2019, Monitoring predators and prey in the Otways.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2019, Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin to benefit both threatened species and agriculture.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Brisbane, November 2018, Modelling invasive predator density in mesic forests.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2018, How many feral cats are in the Otway Ranges?
- ➤ Mathematics of Biological Systems Symposium, Melbourne, April 2018, Integrating co-benefits into the cost-effective prioritisation of conservation strategies.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2018, How many cats are in the Otways?
- ➤ Environmental Institute of Australia & New Zealand conference, Brisbane, August 2017, Building alliances between the agriculture and conservation sectors.

Media

09/12/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Invasive predators interactions
20/09/2019	Television segment feature	TF1 French National News	Invasive animals in Australia
08/08/2019	Radio interview	3AW	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
08/08/2019	Newspaper article (front page)	Geelong Advertiser	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
07/08/2019	Radio interview	ABC South West Victoria	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
13/03/2019	Newspaper article	Colac Herald	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Live TV interview	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Online news article	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Ballarat	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges

Service

- ➤ Peer-reviewer, Wildlife Research, Conservation Biology and Austral Ecology scientific journals (2019-present).
- ➤ Social media manager, QAECO lab twitter account (2019-present).
- ➤ Award judging panel member, Ecological Society of Australia (2020).
- ➤ Treasurer, Biosciences Postgraduate Society (2019-2020).